<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Moh. Sarip Hidayat, S.Tr.Kom</title><link>https://musahi0128.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on Moh. Sarip Hidayat, S.Tr.Kom</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 16:37:00 +0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://musahi0128.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Zabbix setup script for Ubuntu Noble ARM64/AArch64</title><link>https://musahi0128.github.io/posts/solution/monitoring/zabbix-setup-script-noble-arm64/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 16:37:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://musahi0128.github.io/posts/solution/monitoring/zabbix-setup-script-noble-arm64/</guid><description>&lt;p>From &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zabbix" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Wikipedia&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Zabbix is an open-source software tool to monitor IT infrastructure such as networks, servers, virtual machines, and cloud services.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>This script automate the installation of Zabbix Server, Frontend and Agent along with its dependencies. The script was tested on an LXD container using the Ubuntu 24.04.1 image, running in a VM with the &lt;code>VM.Standard.A1.Flex&lt;/code> shape on an Oracle Cloud Infrastructure compute instance. I believe it should work on any machine having the same OS and processor.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>VNC on WSL2</title><link>https://musahi0128.github.io/posts/os/ubuntu/vncserver_wsl2/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 22:55:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://musahi0128.github.io/posts/os/ubuntu/vncserver_wsl2/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Sorry for the tiger eye staring at you. I find it funny so I choose to keep it that way&lt;/em> 🤣&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Windows Subsystem for Linux (WSL) lets developers run a GNU/Linux environment &amp;ndash; including most command-line tools, utilities, and applications &amp;ndash; directly on Windows, unmodified, without the overhead of a traditional virtual machine or dual-boot setup.&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>In my opinion, WSL is just a pre-configured Hyper-V VM or maybe a container which integrate well with Windows.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>VNC on headless VM or container</title><link>https://musahi0128.github.io/posts/os/ubuntu/vncserver_headless/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 00:29:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://musahi0128.github.io/posts/os/ubuntu/vncserver_headless/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Sorry for the tiger eye staring at you. I find it funny so I choose to keep it that way&lt;/em> 🤣&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Headless VM or container didn&amp;rsquo;t have any display device attached, so when you want to run a graphical application or a desktop environment, you will have to setup a virtual display. One way to do it is running a VNC server.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>VNC stands for &lt;strong>V&lt;/strong>irtual &lt;strong>N&lt;/strong>etwork &lt;strong>C&lt;/strong>omputing, a graphical desktop-sharing system that uses the Remote Frame Buffer protocol (RFB) to remotely control another computer. It transmits the keyboard and mouse input from one computer to another, relaying the graphical-screen updates, over a network. Read more &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VNC" title="Virtual Network Computing" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Xfce4 + Papirus icon + Dracula theme = 🖤</title><link>https://musahi0128.github.io/posts/os/ubuntu/xfce4-papirus-dracula/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2024 22:24:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://musahi0128.github.io/posts/os/ubuntu/xfce4-papirus-dracula/</guid><description>&lt;p>I love tinkering with desktop environment in Ubuntu. I installed LXD on my Oracle Cloud Infrastructure A1 instance just to play around with all the available desktop environment. But none of them beat the combination of xfce4, Papirus icon theme and Dracula theme. It is lightweight and pleasant to look at.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img alt="Preview" src="https://musahi0128.github.io/images/posts/tvnviewer_I1l5tQfGOa.png" title="preview">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="setting-up">Setting up&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Wanna steal the look? here&amp;rsquo;s how to configure it on a freshly installed Ubuntu 24.04.1 LTS.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>