<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Monitoring on Moh. Sarip Hidayat, S.Tr.Kom</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/monitoring/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Monitoring on Moh. Sarip Hidayat, S.Tr.Kom</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 22:37:00 +0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/posts/monitoring/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
      <title>Zabbix: monitor host over SSH</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/monitoring/zabbix-host-ssh/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 22:37:00 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/monitoring/zabbix-host-ssh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever stumble upon a situation where you need to configure Zabbix host to be monitored but they are not on the same network?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting up a VPN network would be one of the most suggested approach. But let&amp;rsquo;s says it isn&amp;rsquo;t an option for you, or you don&amp;rsquo;t want to do it that way for any reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to solve this problem is to setup SSH connection between the server and the monitored hosts, and then forward the Zabbix agent port (10050 by default) of the monitored host to a port on the server. This would work if your Zabbix server is accessible by its public IP and able to expose its SSH port. Refer to &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/posts/solution/monitoring/zabbix-setup-script-noble-arm64/&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; on how to setup Zabbix server on a machine with ARM64/AArch64 processor and Ubuntu Noble operating system.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zabbix setup script for Ubuntu Noble ARM64/AArch64</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/monitoring/zabbix-setup-script-noble-arm64/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 16:37:00 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/monitoring/zabbix-setup-script-noble-arm64/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zabbix&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zabbix is an open-source software tool to monitor IT infrastructure such as networks, servers, virtual machines, and cloud services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This script automate the installation of Zabbix Server, Frontend and Agent along with its dependencies. The script was tested on an LXD container using the Ubuntu 24.04.1 image, running in a VM with the &lt;code&gt;VM.Standard.A1.Flex&lt;/code&gt; shape on an Oracle Cloud Infrastructure compute instance. I believe it should work on any machine having the same OS and processor.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>
